All right, so the last video was a
little bit harsh for a scholarship.
Surely there's some grace between having
one and not having one. Maybe you could
get a partial scholarship. Um, and you
can do that in code, too. So, we've said
if they have greater than 3.5, alert,
congrats, here's a scholarship. Well,
what if they have between 3.5 and 3.0?
Let's do that. So we'll say else if
and then we'll put our parenthesis.
And so this is how you make a second
consideration. So you make a first
consideration and you say if it's
greater than 3.5 alert congrats here's a
scholarship. Here it says if it's not
greater than 3.5 um what other
consideration do you want to make? Well
in this case I want to say let's see if
their GPA is greater than or equal to
3.0.
And then right here between these
parentheses, all alert.
Good job. Here is a partial
scholarship.
Whoa, can't spell.
All right. So, what's going to happen
is we're going to gather their GPA. If
they've entered 3.5 exactly, then we're
going to say, is 3.5 greater than 3.5?
It's not. So, we're going to skip there.
Then, we're going to say, well, what if
3 point is 3.5 greater than 3.0? It is.
So, now we can alert, good job. Here's a
partial scholarship. Let's see this in
action. So, I'm going to save this and
come over here and it says, what is your
GPA? I'll put 3.5. Says, good job.
Here's a partial scholarship. If we
reload and we put 3.7, we get, congrats,
here's a scholarship. We reload and we
put uh 2.0. know then we say sorry maybe
next year. So in that way we were able
to have multiple considerations
and you can keep stringing these
together. So I could say else if GPA is
greater than or equal to 2.5
alert
let's see if we can raise your GPA
and then I could say else if GPA is
greater than or equal to 2.0 No
alert
keep trying
and then we'll say else if GPA is
greater than or equal to 1.5
alert
don't worry there are more important
things
than grades
and then finally we'll A. So if they
don't have a GPA of higher than 3.5,
don't have a GPA higher than 3.0, don't
have a GPA higher than 2.5, don't have a
GPA higher than 2.0, and don't have a
GPA higher than 1.5, then we'll say
alert.
Um, looks like your GPA is too low for
this later.
We'll save that
and we'll go check it out. So, it says,
"What is your GPA?" Let's say I enter
3.7. I get, "Congrats, here's a
scholarship." Reload 3.1.
Good job school scholarship. Reload 2.5.
Let's see if we can raise your GPA.
Reload 2.0. Keep trying. Reload. One.
Looks like your GPA is too low for this
calculator. So, we're able to make a lot
of decisions just um based on the GPA.
And so, that is how you use else if you
can make additional decisions if the
first condition is not met. The way an
if statement works, it starts at the top
and it goes to the bottom. So, if it
meets this condition, it will never get
to line 20. It will always go to line
16. If it doesn't meet line 16, then
sorry, if it doesn't meet line 15, then
it'll check line 18. If it doesn't meet
line 18, it'll check line 22. If it
doesn't meet line 22, it'll check line
25. If it meets line 25, then it will
never get to line 28. If it doesn't meet
line 25, then it'll check line 28. If it
doesn't meet line 28, then it will have
met none of these conditions and it will
do the else statement. And that is how
if, else if and else works.